In this video we're going to learn how
to use the Tiny Tapeout GitHub template
to turn your design into the ASIC
files we need to manufacture the chip.
If you don't already have a GitHub
account you'll need to create one.
Then navigate to one of the template
repositories.
We have one for Wokwi designs and
another one for Verilog or other HDLs.
I'll use the Wokwi template for now.
Click the "Use this template" button. This
creates your own copy of the repository.
For open-source projects
GitHub pays for the
cloud compute which we
use to make the ASIC files.
It's turned on by default
but we still need to
allow the actions to
create the results page.
We have the instructions here but I'll
show you how to do it now.
Go to your repository settings page,
"Pages", then set build and deploy source
to "GitHub actions".
Now we're ready to adapt the template to our
own projects by editing the info.yaml file.
For Wokwi projects you need to
change the project's Wokwi ID to match the
number in your Wokwi project.
For HDL projects like Verilog or Amaranth
we use the source file section here.
That's covered in a separate video
called "Working with an HDL".
Okay so let's set the Wokwi ID to
match our project.
I'll copy the last part of the projects
URL and replace the 0 with it.
Most simple designs will fit into one
tile.
If you need more space you can change
the tile setting to get more space.
Bigger designs cost more.
If you're not sure just start with one
and see what happens.
We also need to fill out the title,
author and so on.
If you use Discord then put your Discord
name here and when you submit a design
we'll add you to the Tapeout role.
Further down in the file there's a
section to describe what the pins do.
And this is really useful for testing other
people's designs so please fill it in.
Then hit the commit button to save your
changes.
There's one more file you have to edit,
the info.md inside the docs directory.
This is important for a few reasons.
First is that because everyone who
orders a chip will also get your design.
It's nice if they can understand how to
experiment with it.
The second reason is that by the time the chips come
back you'll probably have forgotten how it works
and you'll be glad you wrote down some
instructions.
You can make the documentation better by adding
pictures and links to extra documentation.
After filling in all the details press
the commit button.
This starts the GitHub actions running.
You can access the results using the
actions tab at the top here.
We have three actions.
One for documentation that shows how your
documentation will look when it's printed
and other will be used for automatic testing of
Wokwi designs if you've used the truth table option.
And finally we have the GDS action
which is used to build the ASIC files for
manufacturing.
If you want to find out more about that we
have a separate video showing how it works.
It's called "How the GitHub action
creates the ASIC files".
Let's take a quick look at the docs
action.
This is useful to see how
your documentation will
be formatted for the
online and print data sheet.
We get a PDF file we
can download and check to
see if the formatting
and the picture works.
Let's take a look at the GDS action
results.
We have this nice page
with some warnings,
utilization statistics
and standard cell usage.
If you don't understand a warning
join us on the Discord chat server
and post in the
GitHub actions channel.
You can take a look at the cells in use
by clicking these links.
For example this X-NOR2 gate.
Let's take a closer look at the 3D
viewer.
Right click to pan, left click to change
the perspective,
scroll wheel to zoom in and out.
On the right we can see which
cells are used and how many,
above we have the
control for layer visibility.
We also have some shortcut keys on the
right.
Pressing "1" hides all the
filler cells, "2" hides the wiring
and "3" isolates
the currently selected cell.
I'd really appreciate it
if you took a screenshot
of your design and
posted it on social media
with a description of what it does
along with a Tiny Tapeout hashtag.
Back on the front page of the
repository you'll see we have these
three green lights now for the
docs, test and GDS all passing.
The GDS status needs to be green to
submit your design.
Sometimes the GDS action will fail.
A Wokwi design should almost always
work.
If not then it's probably our
problem and you should let
us know in the Wokwi channel
of the Discord chat server.
If you're using an HDL it's
usually because of an error
in your design or because
the design is too large.
To get more details you can look
at the logs here in the action results
or download the zipped GDS logs
out of hacked and take a look inside.
First check the
synthesis log file under
runs > wokwi >logs > synthesis >
synthesis.errors for design errors.
If your design is too large
then the failure will normally
be to do with the placement
or routing part of the flow.
You can try to reduce your design
size or upgrade to a larger design
by increasing the number
of tiles in your info.yaml config.
When you're ready to
submit go to tinytapeout.com
and then scroll down to
the submission section.
Click the button to go
to our submission app.
Sign in with your GitHub account
then copy and paste the URL
of your GitHub repository
into the form and press submit.
If you have a coupon you can apply it here
otherwise you'll need to pay to continue.
At this point you've created
your project but it's not yet
part of the Tiny Tapeout. You
have to submit a revision first.
Once that's happened that version of
your design is committed to the shuttle.
If you want to make any changes you need to
come back here and submit a new revision.
So that's it. Happy hacking and I look
forward to seeing what you make on your ASIC.